NIVETHA BALASUBRAMANIAN

Energetic software engineer with 2 years of work experience in creating solutions on Data Science usecases in Python and equipping Devops pipelines to deploy those solutions. Certified Java developer with experience in creating and deploying APIs in Agile development process. Currently looking forward to widen skills and work on Data science projects.

EDUCATION

SSN College Of Engineering, Chennai

June 2014 - April 2018

Affiliated to Anna University

Bachelor of Technology
Department of Information Technology

CGPA: 8.63/10 University Rank: 29

WORK EXPERIENCE

HSBC Technology India, Pune

May 2020 - Present

Software Engineer - Devops Engineer in NPIP Project

- · Developing the infrastructure and pipeline needed to run the Mulesoft APIs by employing Jenkins through Groovy scripts.
- · Developing APIs for Payment Initiation, Membership validation and Payment cancellation usecases.

HSBC Technology India, Pune

July 2018 - April 2020

Software Engineer - Data Engineering in GLCM Innovation Project

- · Developing the infrastructure and pipeline needed to run the Machine Learning Models on Google Cloud Platform, employing Ansible and Jenkins through Terraform scripts.
- · Working on Time Series data to perform Client Clustering, Product Recommendation and Invoice Matching using Machine Learning Models in Python.

Tata Consultancy Services Limited, Chennai

June 2017 - July 2017

Intern - Web Development

· Developed a web application model using Struts2, a back end framework, for a wholesale market company in the United States.

Intellect Design Arena, Chennai

June 2016 - July 2016

Intern - Software Engineering

· Developed a Java module for a banking use case. This experience exposed me to the nuances of the software development life cycle.

PROJECTS

Optimised Feature Selection for Early Cancer Detection

* Analysed the performances of Genetic Algorithm combined with classification techniques like Artificial Neural Network, Logistic Regression etc. on the early categorization of Cancer Cells as Benign/Malignant and devised an optimised Feature Selection technique based on the research.

* Attended National level conference and applied for publication in the journal- Concurrency and Computational: Practice and Experience.

Import & Export Trade Recommendation as a part of Nation-wide Datathon at HSBC

* Secured second position among 60 teams. Built a Sequential model using Keras to develop a trade recommendation system on Google cloud platform using the historical trade data and other features to fit the Gravitation model.

Crop Retail Price Prediction system for Farmers as a part of Facebook-sponsored HerTech Hackathon

* Built a Neural Net model using the historical crop data prices with weather and soil factors to estimate the retail prices. Recognised as one of the top 3 teams among 100+ teams.

COURSES AND CERTIFICATIONS

- * Certified Oracle Java Associate Level Programmer.
- * Completed Coursera courses on Google Cloud Platform and Andrew NG's Machine Learning.
- * Completed NPTEL Courses on Application Development, Machine Learning and Blockchain.
- * Completed Deep Learning course offered by One Fourth Labs.

ACHIEVEMENTS

- * Recognised with Pat on the Back and the Most Consistent Performer award at HSBC Technology India.
- * Secured Twenty Ninth University Rank among 4049 candidates during my Undergraduate course in Information Technology.
- * Acclaimed as one among the top 3 teams in Facebook-sponsored HerTech Hackathon, Pune.
- * Rewarded with Silver medal and scholarship amount worth \$584 for academic excellence.

LANGUAGES

C, C++, Java, Python, HTML, CSS, Javascript, SQL

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Data Mining, Text Mining, Web scraping, Deep Learning

EXTRA CURRICULAR ACHIEVEMENTS

- * Volunteered for conference and monthly events as a part of Women in Data Science group, Pune.
- * Conducted Hands-on session on Google Cloud Platform at Department Level in HSBC Technology India (HTI), Pune for around 30-40 co-employees.
- * Participated in Grace Hopper Celebrations India event 2018 at Bangalore.
- * Organised cultural and CSR events at HSBC.